Okay, good morning or good evening.
And welcome
to Tsongkhapa Day. We call Gaden
Ngamcho.
And it's good to see you guys. Uh
So the very first thing I would like to
do is to
welcome
Jenny Wong from the Singapore group.
Tim, is there some way to do that?
Uh
Yeah, I've asked her to I've asked her
to
you're doing it already.
Working on it.
There she is.
Yeah, hi Jenny.
I like your mask.
Uh
So this special 3-day teaching
is to honor Jenny Wong and the Singapore
group
for many years of hard work, more than
10 years of hard work.
And uh
they have
uh
spent 10 years
helping us all over the world, in
Vietnam,
in Taiwan,
in Malaysia,
in Indonesia,
in Singapore,
and Jenny especially has worked really,
really hard.
Uh
really, really hard. She
She's also learning English and Chinese
both, and I wish I could be like her.
And
and now she's teaching in English and in
Chinese.
And
she's just worked really, really hard.
And her group
is helping us all over the world.
The Singapore group is helping our
children's charity.
More than 500 children
uh
being helped every day
uh at their school and with their
clothing and their food and they have
helped uh build the roads at Diamond
Mountain.
Uh they have helped build many things at
Diamond Mountain.
They have helped uh with the Castle Rock
fund
which is the new uh
sort of a fund to help all of
And I can't even count all the things
that they have done.
And uh so
you know, I called them and I said I how
about I can do a three-day teaching
for free with you guys
and uh we can do it through the
Singapore group.
And uh so I first of all, I just want to
thank you, Jenny, for all your heart
hard work for years of hard work
and all your beautiful staff, all your
friends, all my friends there
uh that work so hard for so many years
and uh
I don't know. Jenny, you want to say hi?
Tim, can we do that?
Uh still can't hear.
Yes, I can hear right now. I can
Try again, Jenny.
Yeah, can you hear me? Can you hear me?
Uh it's okay.
Can you hear me?
Uh can you hear me?
Yeah, we got you, Jenny.
We're good.
Oh, okay. Thank you so much. Thank you,
Geshe
for your
Yeah, I'm so happy to have this event
and then you're teaching us for three
days. Thank you so much. Yeah, it's my
honors can do these things with ACI team
and
Diamond Press. Thank you so much.
Okay, cool. I couldn't hear, but
everyone else can hear, so it's good.
And thank you, Jenny, again.
Uh
So, today is the
uh Ganden Ngamchoe,
which we call the uh 25th of the 10th
month.
So, the moon to the black moon, it's 5
days away.
And this is considered the new year
uh in Mongolia, for example.
Uh in fact, uh today is Sonkapa's
birthday.
And uh passing away day.
And also enlightenment day. So, all
three
uh happen on this day.
And uh it's so important in Mongolia
that uh everybody uh celebrates this day
as their birthday.
So, never ask a Mongolian person what is
their birthday.
Uh
because the answer is always the same.
and this is the
tradition.
Uh
let me check my speaker.
okay, Tim.
My speaker's on. I hope so.
Uh
okay, let me check here.
Okay.
I think my speaker's on, Tim.
You want to test it?
Can you hear me now?
Yeah, good. Okay. All right, thank you.
I'm sorry.
Uh and Irina, if I forget to do anything
today, you remind me, okay? Cuz uh
it's difficult for me to look at all the
things at the same time. So, we're going
to have a special uh tradition
on Sonkapa day
that we light a thousand lamps.
And this is called Tongchoe. And Tong
means uh 1,000.
And Cho means a offering
of uh 1,000
uh
butter lamps.
And I put some lamps on this Christmas
tree
uh for Tsongkhapa.
Uh so that's my
that's my beginning of my
uh
butter lamps
uh for Tsongkhapa.
And I can see in Singapore, Taiwan,
Diamond Mountain, and Malaysia, you guys
have already started your
butter lamps.
Uh
and
let's light them now, okay?
And these teachings of Tsongkhapa
are like the light for the whole world.
And uh
you can think that the world is like
darkness.
And without these teachings,
uh the world is is dark.
It's black. Uh even in the daytime, the
world is black.
And it means uh
you know, different people have
different ways to be successful.
Uh different people have different ways
of living.
But really uh in the end, uh we all have
to die.
Uh everyone gets old.
Uh everyone gets tired.
Everybody's body breaks.
And they leave this world. And and we
don't see them after them. And
And there's only one real hope to change
that.
And that's if we can practice
uh this teaching of Tsongkhapa very
well.
Uh
we can change that for the whole world.
So it's like uh this teaching of
Tsongkhapa is like a light.
And uh
so we
on his birthday,
uh we like to offer the the special
lights.
So you guys can start lighting and I
will also light.
And
several people burned down their house
this way.
Uh but hopefully we won't do.
Okay.
All right, good.
And thank you guys. I can see you in
Taiwan, Singapore.
Uh Diamond Mountain. They're very
beautiful.
Malaysia, Japan.
Uh thank you for lighting.
So, when you light the lamp,
uh just imagine
that this is the light in the world
that gives people hope
uh to stop the darkness of death,
uh the darkness of old age, uh darkness
of war,
uh darkness of sickness in the world.
And that's the purpose of what we do.
Uh it's the purpose of what all of us
are are spending every day,
and why we work so hard.
Uh it's to put this light in the world.
And uh I I believe it's the only hope
that the world has
uh to stop death,
uh to stop death not just for this
world, but for many many worlds,
countless worlds.
We're not the only world
in the universe. There are
countless worlds in the universe. There
are countless beings in the universe.
And
if you study some compass teaching,
uh if you learn them,
uh you can meet those people and that's
fun. I mean, if you think about it,
uh, to meet all the people on other
planets. I enjoy just flying to other
countries.
But, if you study Tsongkhapa's teaching,
then
actually, you can go to
you can travel to countless planets.
And, uh,
and it's an amazing experience. It's a
incredible experience. It's a great
experience for me to go to Russia
or go to Singapore,
uh, go to Japan.
But, imagine, uh, the experience to go
to,
uh, countless worlds
and and visit the people there
and help them
and be a light for them. So,
try to remember that, uh, during these 3
days.
Uh, in these 3 days,
uh, we'll be talking about, uh, the
story
of Tsongkhapa,
uh, his life story.
Uh,
not because of history. Uh, it's not
because of a history lesson. I I
actually, I'm not very interested in
history or what's the date of somebody
or something like that. I I don't think
it's
so helpful for the world, but,
we're going to study his life
inside of his mind.
You know, we're going to study what was
he thinking about.
And, what was he doing,
uh, to be a light in this world, you
know, because
we can also be a light
for this world. Well, we are we also
have all the equipment
the same as Tsongkhapa. We are not
different from him.
Uh,
we have the ability and we have the
chance,
uh, to help the whole world. You are not
uh
far away from this ability. You have
met the teachings of Sopa.
Uh you understand how to meditate.
Uh you understand about emptiness.
Uh you understand about good karma.
So, we are not uh very far away from
Sopa.
And we can also be a light for the whole
world. Okay? And I don't see Sopa as
coming from one country.
Uh
I feel like he's uh
a teacher for the whole world.
So,
in this
in these 3 days, we're going to talk
about a special book.
This is the book.
Uh
it's called King of the Dharma.
And
uh
this is a
book that I finished about 20 years ago.
And I'm going to tell you the story
about the book.
And this book came out uh this the this
uh
the new edition came out uh this month.
And it's coming out in English and also
in Chinese.
Uh
there's some countries where we are not
allowed to publish this book and we are
not publishing it
in those countries, but in Singapore, in
United States,
and
other places where it's allowed,
uh we have published this book. Uh
And I want to tell you the story about
the book.
So, uh
I don't know.
I spent 25 years.
Uh I was a student
of my teacher, Khenpo Che
Geshe Lobsang Tharchin
in a small
uh Mongolian
temple.
Uh there's a picture here. Let me see.
You can see this picture. Kind of you
can see.
Uh
it was a very very cold place
uh near New York. And it's a small
Mongolian temple. We have about 15 monks
there.
Not much.
And uh all of the monks average age is
about 75 years old.
Uh they are refugees
uh from World War II.
And they are living in in America and uh
they built uh
three or four big temples there.
Uh very difficult. They didn't have any
money.
They built the temples with their own
hands.
And they brought uh great teachers there
from
Mongolia, from Kalmykia, which is uh
Mongol people in Europe.
And from Tibet and from India. They
brought teachers
uh great great teachers came there.
And so during the hippie times
uh which is my favorite time
uh
we some hippies came to those temples.
And they actually they were from some
very good universities uh from Harvard.
Uh four famous hippies came there.
And from Princeton University and we met
those great lamas, great teachers.
And we tried to learn how to speak
Tibetan.
Uh we tried to learn how to read the
ancient books.
And I also became a monk uh through that
temple.
And I lived at that temple for 25 years.
Uh
and I studied with my teacher.
Uh later he took me to the
main Sera monastery.
And that's when I did my Geshe studies.
But I remember this temple.
And it was very beautiful part of my
life.
Uh
So, I was studying there.
And we used to have uh
all the monks will get together
on a holiday and we will pray together
in the temple.
And there's a few Tibetan monks and
mostly Mongolian monks
uh from Kalmyk Mongol. This is uh Mongol
near Russia.
Near South Russia.
And uh lucky I learned how to speak
Russian uh in my university.
So, lucky I was able to talk with them.
And I learned to speak Tibetan with the
Tibetans.
Uh
But uh when we do the prayers
uh
the main uh teacher
uh the main monk, he was blind.
He he couldn't see.
He was a very uh high high Geshe from
Tibet.
Uh but he was born in Mongolia.
And so he was Mongolian.
And he was very stubborn man. And he
insists
to
lead the prayers
uh even though he cannot read.
Uh
But he memorized all the prayers.
So, he will lead the prayers and we
don't have choice. We have to follow
him.
You know? And he will go like this.
Then it goes very very fast, you know.
And uh
even I cannot find the book he's
reciting
uh before he's finished.
You know.
He will finish the prayer. I'm still
looking for what the book he's praying.
You know. Uh and I
I got all the books, all the possible
books. I have a big stack around me.
And when he starts the prayer, I will
grab the right book and I will try to
find the
the page. Uh
But sometimes it's just impossible. He
will
he will memorize some ancient prayer. I
don't know the prayer.
And actually I got angry. I I used to
get upset.
And uh I used to go on strike.
So strike means uh I don't even try to
to follow the other monks. Sometimes I
will fake fake reciting.
And uh
sometimes I'm too angry even to fake it.
You know. And uh
so I just sit there and ignore
everybody.
And I will look at the temple. It's a
beautiful temple.
It has many many uh beautiful paintings
uh from Mongolia.
And uh old paintings uh
And then high high high in the temple
there are some strange thankas.
Uh 15 strange
uh Tibetan paintings, you know.
And I couldn't see them very clearly. Uh
I could see Tsongkhapa
is in each uh thanka.
But I couldn't see them. Then uh
my teacher used to have a retreat every
summer
in New Jersey and it's very hot. The
weather is very very hot.
And uh he'd tell me, "We don't have air
conditioning."
And uh he gets a big ladder.
And he tells me, "You go open the
windows at the top of the church, you
know, top of the temple."
The the temple is three four stories
high.
And I have a special ladder.
It's like I don't know
uh
It's like 20 m.
20 or 30 m high.
And I have to climb up the ladder.
And I have to open the window.
Uh
And it's very frightening for me. And
there's nobody to help me.
And uh
But sometime I go up there
to open the window.
And I can see this painting, Tsongkhapa
painting, close.
And I realize it's 15 different
paintings.
Each one is different. Each one has
Tsongkhapa in the middle.
And then each painting has many small
paintings next to it.
And uh
then I can see, if I look very
carefully,
I can see some
writing
on the painting. There's some tiny tiny
writing on the painting
in Tibetan language.
Uh
And I got uh very interested about these
paintings. And I studied them for 15
years.
I wrote down all of the writing.
I studied what's going on in each
painting.
And then I realized these are the life
story
of Tsongkhapa. And not his history,
but the story of his mind
and the story of his heart.
Uh what's happening inside his heart
uh for his whole life, 600 years ago,
is in this paintings, you know? And I
was so
happy to find them and and uh
So, anyway, uh
I decided to make a book about the
paintings.
Uh when I went to the
uh Biblioteca of Vostokovedeniya
in Petersburg,
I found the
the woodblock carving
about the painting, how to how to write
the history of Sonam Gyaltsen.
I found that book in Russia
in the St. Petersburg Library. And John
Brady's project was there for
12 years.
We cataloged 141,000
books.
And one of those books
is the story how to paint those
paintings.
Uh so, I used the book
and I translated it
and I made this book.
Uh
And this book has three parts.
By the way, Tim, if you want to
Well, let's do later.
This book has three parts, okay? First
part
is the story of the temple.
Uh like what's the story, how was this
temple built?
This is my teacher
uh sitting in the temple.
And
uh
the first uh part of the book
is all about uh
my teacher
and how he came to this temple. He was
sent there
by the Dalai Lama.
And how he taught
all the hippies there.
So, it's a very cute story
about how the hippies came to
New Jersey.
And those hippies became great uh
professors all over the world.
Uh
they became uh the great translators.
here you can see the
This is the uh
the top of the temple and the
chandelier.
So, the first part of this book is all
about uh
Here's the book from Russia.
Uh one page from the book in Russia.
It tells you how to paint the paintings,
okay?
And then in the last part of the book
is uh all the paintings themselves
uh with the original
manuscript, okay? And it took many, many
years to finish.
And each thangka
Here's one thangka.
Uh here's one painting. There are 15
paintings and uh
each painting has tiny, tiny letters.
And
here's the
letters and here's the meaning
of each part of Tsongkhapa's inner life,
okay? His inside life.
So, there's uh 100
150, over 150
stories
about Tsongkhapa's
inner life, his inside life.
Ever since he was a kid
up until
the day he passed away, which is today.
Uh
and that's the last part of the book,
the third part of the book.
And it took many, many years to finish
it.
It was very, very difficult
uh
but we finished it.
So, the first part of the book is the
history
of these paintings and these hippies
uh including Geshe Michael.
And
uh
the last part of the book is the all the
paintings
and each different part of each painting
and it it was 15 years of hard work. It
was very very difficult work.
Uh in the middle of the book is the big
part of the book.
And
we talk about uh Tsongkhapa's life.
And what did he do in his life? Okay?
So, I think this is the important part
of the book.
The paintings are very interesting.
Uh the history of his life,
what did he do each year of his life.
The first part is interesting about the
hippies
and how the Mongolians came to America,
how they
how they built their temples
and how they got these paintings. How
did they get these paintings? Where did
these paintings come from?
But the inside of the book, the middle
of the book,
it tells you how to live like
Tsongkhapa.
Uh each part of his life.
Okay? So, like here it's uh how to do
retreat.
Uh
And how did he do his retreat?
Uh this one talk about he learned how to
dance. He learned to do uh religious
dancing, spiritual dancing.
And how can we do dancing
ourselves? How can we do spiritual
dancing, you know?
Uh
This one
This one story of how he saw emptiness
directly.
And uh you can see
uh
Manjushri put a sword in his heart.
Uh Manjushri put a sword inside of
Tsongkhapa's heart.
And then he saw emptiness directly. So,
the purpose of this book is to give you
some
uh
guide book
some map
how you can do like Tsongkhapa, how to
learn to dance like him,
how to learn to see emptiness like him,
how to learn to meditate, how to learn
to do retreat,
all the big things he did in his life
uh are in this book. And And it's a
great book, okay? And it's Now it's
available.
We just finished the paperback. So it's
much cheaper.
And you can order the book uh from the
Diamond Cutter Press.
It took me about uh 15 years to finish
the paperback
uh because it was a lot of work to
change the book uh to paperback. Uh but
now it's available this month.
Uh 15 years of hard work, 30 years
total.
And uh
This book I made uh to donate the money
to the Mongol small Mongolian temple
in New Jersey where the hippies learned
uh
and me, where we learned Tibetan, where
we learned to read the ancient books.
And we are always donating the profit
of the book uh
to that temple. So we made a hard copy
uh
20 years ago.
15 17 years ago.
And uh
we sold it uh Jenny Wong's group sold
many copies for us. Thank you.
And we donated all the money to this
small temple
so they can teach the hippies of the
next generation
and the next generation. And uh
So this book also we're going to donate
all the profits uh to the temple. We
will pay our staff
for their work. We will pay for the
paper
and the book and then we will donate to
the temple.
And so far it's been very successful and
we help the temple a lot.
Uh and it helped them to stay
healthy
and to invite more monks there.
And those monks are now teaching. That's
now a third generation
is teaching there, okay?
I'm going to uh
We had a
So some museums asked me to come there
and talk about these paintings.
So I went to some museums in New York.
I went to the National Museum of
Argentina
and other museums and I talked
about these
uh
this book and about these paintings.
And I realized it's too much to teach in
in 1 hour or 2 hours. It's impossible to
talk about
So Karma's life in 1 hour or 2 hours.
So I decided to pick
important things he did with his life.
important practices he did with in his
lifetime.
And these are 12 things that you and I
can learn how to do.
And uh so I made a 12
posters
that people can keep in their house.
And
and you can put the posters on the wall.
And these are the 12
big things that you can do
and I can do
if we want to be like So Karma. If we
want to see emptiness
if we want to learn to meditate
if we want to be a light in the world
there are 12 different
main things he did. 12 main things he
did.
And then we thought Jenny Wong and me
and we had a plan.
Uh
because Soka Gakkai's birthday is today
and New Year's Western New Year's is in
2 days from now.
Uh we thought let's have his birthday
and let's have 3 days of teaching
about his life and then we can have New
Year's celebration
together.
Uh so we will celebrate the New Year
Western New Year on midnight in
Singapore.
Uh which is also uh midnight in Beijing
uh also Indonesia parts of Malaysia. So
we're going to celebrate
uh the day after tomorrow.
Uh we will invite all guests from uh
mainland China also
and from other countries around the
world.
Uh for me it would be uh 9:00 in the
morning
but I don't mind to celebrate with you
guys.
Uh for Europeans it will be afternoon.
That's okay. I know you guys you start
your champagne a little bit early
usually anyway.
So uh in Russia, right Katrin? So uh
uh we can celebrate at the same time.
Uh for Alex Rivera and me it's you are 1
hour ahead of me I think. Uh but anyway
uh we can start celebrate the New Year
together.
Uh this broadcast is not allowed in in
mainland China because it's religious
and I'm not allowed to teach religion in
mainland China.
Uh so we cannot uh show this broadcast
for 2 days but the third day
uh will not be religious. We will not
show religious books.
And on the third day we will invite our
friends from China, mainland China,
also.
And we won't talk about religious
subjects. So,
here we go. I'm going to share my
screen.
And I'm going to show you these 12
main
main activities that Tsongkhapa did in
his life, okay? 12 main things.
And if we can learn to do the 12,
we can be like him.
And and we can be a light in this world,
for many many worlds, countless worlds.
And you can do it, okay?
You won't get a better chance.
You won't get a better chance. You have
a healthy body.
You are not too old like grandpa. I just
turned 69 a few days ago.
You're young.
You're strong.
You can meditate. You have good teachers
like Genny.
You can meditate.
You can practice.
And you can be like Tsongkhapa, okay?
It's not crazy idea.
Okay? We have to plan about it. And you
can be like Tsongkhapa. There's no
reason why not.
You have all the teaching.
You have enough food.
You're not refugee, okay? You have
comfortable life.
And there's no reason why you you can't
do it. So, we're going to study
12 different things that Tsongkhapa did
in his life.
And so, two days
we will cover 12
different posters.
And I made them with Rob Russinger. He's
the former president of Diamond Mountain
Retreat Center.
He's a great great man. He's a really
great man.
And it's a big honor to know him.
And he worked on this book for many
years, also. He laid out the whole book.
And we worked for many years together.
He and he didn't charge any money. In
fact, he donated the money for the first
printing.
Uh
so, he donated all his time
and he donated his money. And uh so,
we made 12 posters
to show the story of Tsongkhapa from the
paintings. We took the
sexy parts from the paintings
and then we added some hippie things
also
uh to the paintings to make them fun.
Okay. So, I'm going to show you the 12
new posters
and we will study them together. Each
poster
has one part of Tsongkhapa's life.
His inner life.
And for 2 days
I will teach you the posters which I
made from the paintings
uh with Rob Brezsny.
And then on the third day, when the
mainland uh friends can come also,
we won't talk about religion.
Uh we won't show the religious
paintings.
But we will talk about our plan
together for the new year. So, what's
your plan?
What's my plan
uh to improve my life. Okay? It's a
custom
in America and other countries uh on the
new year,
you also make some promises for the new
year. So, Jenny, usually it's uh
we like to overeat too much during
Christmas time.
And grandpa also gained a lot of weight
this month. And usually
uh we make a promise on on New Year,
like we will eat more careful.
We won't eat meat. We won't drink
alcohol.
Uh we will exercise every day.
Uh Uh
or we will treat our family better.
Or we won't yell at our boss or
something like that. We make a promise
on the new year. So, my suggestion
together
on the new year, three third day of this
teaching,
let's all make our promise together.
Uh you can make some problem promise for
the new year.
And for 2 days, I will give you some
choices
about what promise you can make, okay?
So, I will give you some
choices
about some compass' favorite practices.
And then, uh think about it for today
and tomorrow.
Uh
which one do you want to make your
promise
for the new year? And then on the third
day,
when we have all the friends from
mainland China also, we can make our
promise together.
Uh you can make some promise for the new
year, okay? Usually, Jenny, we break the
promise within 3 weeks or 4 weeks.
But, uh that's okay.
Uh
at least we can get some good seeds
uh from keeping the promise. Uh
some people keep it for the whole year.
And those are very good people. Uh so,
I'm going to share my screen now, Tim.
Uh let me see here.
So, these are the posters which I made.
Let me see if I can change this.
Uh
Yeah, these are the posters
that I made uh together with uh Rob
Brassington
uh almost 20 years ago.
And each poster has a story.
Each poster says, "You can do this."
Or you can do this. Or you can do this,
you see? So, there are 12 posters.
And these 2 days, I will teach you the
12 posters.
There are a lot of pictures from uh
Tsongkhapa's life.
Uh the main pictures are from
Tsongkhapa's life, but I mix in some
Me and Rob, we mix in some other
pictures. Okay, this is my teacher. I
put him inside the Tsongkhapa
poster
because he's important for me.
So, this is my teacher.
Uh he's sitting in the Mongolian temple.
And uh
This is a very rare
uh statue. This photograph, the black
and white.
Uh this is a statue of Tsongkhapa.
And it was made uh while he was alive,
600 years ago.
So, this statue was made
of uh Tsongkhapa. His uh people who
don't like him 600 years ago,
they call him Mr. Big Ears.
Or they call him Mr. Big Nose, Nagu
Chimbo.
Uh cuz he had a very big nose, and he
had big ears.
And uh
this statue was made 600 years ago.
And this photograph was made
in 1940.
Uh and
when Tsongkhapa saw the statue,
he immediately he said, "Wow, that looks
like me."
You know, that looks like me. In Tibetan
language, it's Ngadak Ngadama Ngada.
Means, "Hey, it looks like me."
It really looks like me, you know? And
then uh
that statue's name
is Ngadama. Ngadama means uh the looks
like me statue, okay? And it was
destroyed
uh during the
Cultural Revolution in in China.
Uh
but we have one photograph of the
of the painting.
Um
the the hands were covered by
uh
a scarf in the photograph.
And uh my mom, my stepmom, some of you
know her, she's 95 years old.
Uh she
she
she got the hands back.
She she got the hands back on the
picture.
So, uh this is a real picture of some
Kapa, okay?
This first poster
name
is uh find your heart teacher, okay? You
should try to find your heart teacher.
And
if there's 12 most important things
which some Kapa did in his life,
the first one
and the always the most important one
is to find your teacher.
Find your heart teacher, okay? Uh you
can have many teachers. I have about 15
main teachers.
Uh but only one heart teacher, okay?
Heart teacher is the one
who helped you the most in this life,
okay?
Uh
and here you can see the Can you see my
cursor, Tim? Does it show?
Yes, it does.
It does? Okay. So, here's the word guru
in Sanskrit.
Uh Jenny, what's this word in Chinese,
laoshi?
Uh
jin jin
laoshi
jin
jin laoshi, yeah.
Uh heart teacher.
xin laoshi
Oh, xin laoshi, yeah.
Xin laoshi. So, we put this uh Chinese
and Sanskrit. This Sanskrit is guru.
And guru means uh heart teacher, okay?
And this are all stories how Tilopa his
heart teacher.
And he worked hard
to find his heart teacher. Uh I'm happy
to be your heart teacher, but I don't
have to be your heart teacher.
Uh everybody
has different
different feelings. Everybody has
different capacity.
Everybody has
different teacher, maybe I think uh your
heart teacher.
Finding your heart teacher is like
finding your uh
like a pair of jeans, okay? I took uh
Veronica to buy a pair of jeans
at the store. She tried 40 pairs.
She tried on 40 pairs of jeans. You know
this women store, they don't even have
chair for the husband to sit.
You know, you have to stand
and wait for the lady to try on 40 pairs
of jeans. Hey Jenny, guess how many
pairs she bought?
25?
She didn't buy any.
Like 40 pairs. We are there for 2 hours.
She didn't buy any, okay? Then a heart
teacher.
Heart teacher is similar. Heart teacher
is similar, okay? You have to find your
own one.
You have to find your own heart teacher.
Geshe La doesn't
doesn't fit everybody's
Geshe La is like jeans, you know? And
everyone has a different heart teacher.
Uh you have to
you have to look in your life
to find your heart teacher. You have to
check. You have to check many teachers.
And you have to check the teacher
carefully.
And you have to see how is your feeling.
How do you feel about them, okay?
And then then you can
choose a heart teacher, okay? I have one
friend. He says his heart teacher is his
dog.
You know,
uh I have another friend. He says his
heart teacher is his son, his baby son.
Like my tree, you know, and uh
we don't know who's your heart teacher,
okay? That's up to you.
Uh so, here are some parts of the
painting.
Uh
that's Tsongkhapa in the middle.
Uh on his own right side,
his right hand,
so not our left, not our right side, his
right side,
this this lama here,
this is uh Gyaltsab Je.
And that was his number one
uh disciple. After Tsongkhapa passed
away,
then Gyaltsab Je uh became the main
teacher. Uh
and Gyaltsab means that he took over the
teaching after the teacher passed away,
okay?
He was a very great uh book writer.
And in fact, uh Nick Lashaw, Professor
Nick,
who's the head of the uh Mixed Nuts
translation group, Diamond Cutter
Classics,
he is translating
two of Gyaltsab Je's books, and you can
get them soon.
Okay?
Uh over here is uh
the other main disciple.
His name is uh Kedrub Je.
And he was the second main disciple of
Tsongkhapa.
And uh he wrote some great great books
about emptiness. Uh he wrote very very
famous books about emptiness, and uh
Utpala uh is translating them. Uh the
Mixed Nuts translator is translating
them. One of those books is finished.
We finished it uh last month.
And Tim, I don't know if you can show
it.
Uh it's called the
emptiness meditations. It's about it's
over 400 pages, I think.
And it took us about uh 5 or 6 years to
finish.
And
can you see it, Tim?
Uh that's this book. If you want to get
this book,
if you want to get the Tsoknyi book,
uh you can get this QR code.
And uh this is the English. The the
Singapore group is is uh
publishing the Chinese version in
Chinese language. Here's the emptiness
meditations book.
And uh this is uh translated by the
Mixed Nuts.
We just finished this book.
And this book just came out. Uh it's an
ebook.
And you can get it in about uh 1 minute.
I I I'm very happy.
Uh we we have the ebook. So, you can
order it
in about 1 minute. And I like to give
them to my friends. I ordered one copy
for my neighbor. My neighbor's always
curious, "Who is this strange guy living
next to me?"
And uh I sent him uh
this book by email. Uh you can do it in
about
1 minute. You can send the book to your
friend.
Okay? And this is uh new translation
of how to meditate on emptiness.
This comes from the uh Mixed Nuts.
And it's unbelievable. It's a
unbelievable how to meditate.
And there's 30
eight
I think 38 emptiness meditations in this
book.
Uh so, I encourage you to to get the
And I think it's nice to uh give it away
to to your friends. You know, you can
just send the ebook to your friend in
about 1 minute.
Okay.
And then the money helps to support the
translators. Uh we we we helps to
support all our translators.
Hey Miss V, you want to say hi?
Okay. Okay.
All right, I'm going to share my screen
again, Tim. Is that okay?
All right.
Uh
Where is that?
Hm.
No, not that one.
Uh hang on.
Yeah, here we go.
Oh.
Let me see.
Oh, I see. Tim, I have to change the
I have to change this.
I think you'll have to stop sharing and
reshare again.
I have to stop the I have to stop the
focus thing, I think.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay, hang on. Hang on. Hang on.
Uh
Stop the share.
Go to here.
Aiya.
Okay, hang on.
Uh
Okay.
And
And back to screen share.
Aiya.
Well, let's do it this way.
No.
Not here. Okay. Now, can you see it,
Tim?
The posters?
No, it's showing There they are. There
it is.
Okay, good.
All right.
Uh so, I'll tell you some of uh
how Tsongkhapa found his own heart
teacher.
Uh
in this in this part of the painting
here.
Uh,
he's the studying Lamrim.
Okay? He also studied Lamrim here.
And, uh,
this is how he studied, uh, with his own
teacher
to learn about how to find a teacher.
So, even Tsongkhapa
studied with his own teacher
how to find a teacher.
Okay? And that's part of the painting.
You can find it here. Okay?
In the book, you can find it.
Uh,
let me see something.
By the way, this monk here
is the first Dalai Lama, uh,
600 years ago.
Okay? His name is Gedun Drupa. He's also
a student of Tsongkhapa. Okay?
And you can see him
also. He's one of the monks in the
group. Okay?
And
let's see.
Here, uh, Tsongkhapa again
is studying, uh, how to go to a teacher,
how to study with the teacher.
Uh,
this is the first day that Tsongkhapa
met, uh, first Dalai Lama. At that time,
first Dalai Lama was not a monk and he
you can see he has a mustache and a
beard.
And, uh,
later he became a monk.
Uh,
here's my own teacher.
Uh, Khen Rinpoche Geshe Lobsang Tarchin.
And here is Tsongkhapa asking for,
uh, to become, uh, let me see.
He's asking for Diamond Way initiation
from his teacher.
So, this shows us uh
how do we
what's the best way to
to ask your teacher and you can see even
some Karma who is so great,
he is kneeling down
and he is respecting his teacher. So,
it's very important uh when you are
trying to find a teacher.
Uh
after you make a connection with the
teacher,
uh you have to
show them a lot of respect. If you don't
show them respect, uh it doesn't hurt
the teacher,
but uh your practice won't be so good.
Your meditation won't be so good. You
will not see emptiness. You So, you have
to
choose teacher carefully.
Take your time.
Uh don't choose the first teacher you
meet. I heard somebody met a monk in the
airport
and they they asked the monk to become
their teacher after 5 minutes. Uh this
too fast, okay?
Take your time.
Check out this person. Ask their other
students.
But, after you
become their student,
then you have to respect them. You have
to show them a lot of respect, okay? And
here it's on Karma is showing us he's
here. It's on Karma is kneeling down and
he's showing a lot of respect to his
teacher, okay? So, that's very important
if you want to have this relationship
with your teacher, okay? So, that's the
first of the 12 posters.
By the way, we made uh these posters
into calendar
for the new year.
And uh you can get the calendar.
You can get all 12 posters with the
calendar for 2022.
And uh Tim is showing the
Tim is showing the QR code, I think.
And
uh
you can get uh
all of these 12 posters in a calendar,
okay?
Uh all right, I'm going to show you the
second poster.
And then maybe we have some question and
answer. Okay? So, Tim, I'll spend about
5 minutes on the second poster.
And then we can have question and
answer.
This is uh in the new year,
I think a good thing to do
is to try to save the world. Okay? Try
to help the whole world. And this second
poster
is about how to help the whole world.
What can I do?
What can I do to help the whole world?
Okay?
And this is the meaning of this second
poster.
Uh
in the new year
of 2022,
what can each person do
to help the whole world? What can we do
to help the whole world?
You know, when you're born,
when you're a kid,
you feel you see the super
hero movie like Spider-Man. New
Spider-Man movie. Hey, Jenny, I didn't
see it yet, but I'm planning. Okay?
New Spider-Man.
Uh
Then when I was a kid, I asked my mom,
uh "Hey, Mom,
I I
I want to be like Spider-Man."
She said, "Do you know how Spider-Man
became Spider-Man?"
Then I said, "Yeah, I read in the comic
book, in the manga.
Uh he got bitten by a radio action
spider, radioactive spider.
Then he got superpower
from the spider bite." So, for like 3
years,
when I was a kid, I tried to Every time
I see a spider, I tried to get bit by
the spider.
Uh because I think I also will become
super like Spider-Man, you know?
And uh we all want to be superhero.
That's why we like the superhero movie,
you know? And you can,
okay? If you study this book,
if you study Tsongkhapa's life,
if you do what Tsongkhapa did,
you can be a superhero. You can do it,
okay? You can really do it. Here's the
Sanskrit here. It's Bodhicitta.
Okay? Bodhicitta.
I don't know, Jenny, is the Is the
Chinese Bodhicitta here?
Uh Chinese Bodhicitta?
Puti xin.
Puti xin. Yeah, same thing, right?
So, uh
These are some suggestions
how to become uh Bodhisattva. I'll give
you some
Here's one important picture here.
Uh
Tsongkhapa had a good relation with
Chinese emperor, you know? Chinese
emperor
uh wrote to Tsongkhapa.
He invited Tsongkhapa to come to uh the
capital of the empire.
And this uh Chinese government officials
came to to meet Tsongkhapa.
And Tsongkhapa sent his main student,
uh Jam yang Shay drel, to go to
uh Beijing to meet the the emperor.
And there was a good relationship. Uh
so, Tsongkhapa
recognized that it's important
for every country to cooperate with each
other.
Uh he he support
this idea
that uh all people, all different kinds
of people,
all different kinds of countries, uh in
his own life,
uh he was a international
diplomat.
He He was very uh careful
to bring countries together, uh to to
meet people from different countries.
and here you can see he's meeting uh
people from different places in China,
okay?
And
so he's giving us an example
that if we want our meditation to be
good, if we want our practice to be
good, uh we should cooperate with other
countries' people
and with our with many different races,
different languages, different
religions, uh we should cooperate with
each other. We should help each other,
okay?
So that's from the paintings. You can
see his good example, okay?
Uh
this is a beautiful uh
picture
of uh
Tsongkhapa
had a special
vision when he was meditating.
And he's
he's uh meditating and he saw all these
holy beings, you know?
And uh you can see Atisha's here
and the other great Hear the Gardena
and these are the great teachers of the
Lamrim.
And in his meditation
he saw all the great teachers of the
Lamrim.
And they said, "Look, Tsongkhapa, if you
want to help the world,
if you really want to help the whole
world,
then you should study Lamrim.
You should learn Lamrim
uh many years. You should study Lamrim
and you should translate, you should
write about it.
And that's the example you see here. Why
did Tsongkhapa write Lamrim?
Why did he write the greatest book
about the steps of the path to
enlightenment? Why did he write it?
Uh
these guys told him to, okay? The
Gardena
uh
Atisha, these great teachers, they told
him,
"If you really want to help this world,
then you should study Lamrim.
You should practice the steps of the
path.
You should
keep doing
uh Lamrim, and please write the book
about the Lamrim." So, for example, the
ACI courses,
the first course, number one, course
number one,
is about the Lamrim.
And we spent uh I don't know, I spent uh
10 years
teaching you guys Lamrim.
And we have 10 more years to go, okay?
But here is uh Buddha
telling Tsongkhapa,
"If you really want to help the world,
then you should study Lamrim, and you
should practice Lamrim. If you really
want to help this world,
then you should become a Lamrim master,
okay? And this is the meaning of this
painting, okay?
I put a quotation from the Yoga Sutra,
you know, "If you really believe
that the world is coming from seeds,
then
if you don't like war, if you don't like
to see war in the world,
if you don't like to see different
countries fighting with each other,
if you don't like to see violence in
your family,
if you don't like to see fighting in
your own family,
if you really want to help the world,
then change your seeds, okay? Change
your own seeds. If you don't have
violence in your own heart,
then you will see violence disappear in
the world. This is the way to change the
world.
Uh
you know, it's not that you have a super
war,
and you kill all the people who are
making war.
That's not the answer, okay? The answer
is
uh stop the emotion of war
inside your own heart
and then the war will stop in the world.
You can stop war in this world,
but you have to stop it in your own
heart first, okay?
Uh
this is my favorite uh one of my
favorite parts of the painting.
This one here.
And uh
at that time there was no big uh
monastery
in the middle of Tibet. There was no
place to go to study, no place to go to
retreat.
Uh no place to to study the books, no
place to learn to be mixed not
translated. There was no place.
So Tsongkhapa and his uh five students,
just six people,
they decide, "We should build
a place for people to study.
We should build a new place for people
to study."
And uh
Tsongkhapa said, "Okay, we need some
money, you know."
And they uh all check their pockets, how
much money they have.
Hey Jenny, can you guess how much?
The first day the first day they start
to build uh retreat center
and university, how much money they
have?
They they collect all the money, $5.
$5 US. Okay? They have $5.
And they say,
"We only have $5."
Then Tsongkhapa said, "Okay, let's
start. We can buy some rocks
and uh we will do the labor ourselves."
Uh so here they are building
uh Ganden Monastery.
This is Tsongkhapa's main monastery.
Uh
and it became like Diamond Mountain
Retreat Center.
It became like uh DCI S C I M College.
And
it's a hard work. This is a hard work.
And they start with no money.
They start with $5.
And they start with some bricks, you
know. And we have to do the same. If you
want to help this world,
uh you have to make like Jenny Wong
Singapore group, Malaysia group,
Indonesia group.
Uh
you have to work hard. And you don't
have money in the beginning. That's
okay.
Uh
the main problem is not money.
The main problem is courage
and determination.
And then you can build a group. It took
Jenny 10 years, 12 years.
You can build a group.
You can build a university. You can
build a retreat center.
Uh you just need courage. You need to
have courage. You have to decide to do.
Okay? Uh
all those temples, all those stupas,
all those
colleges, all those retreat centers,
it's all the same.
They all start with no money.
And they all start with a few brave
people. B- brave people, okay? Don't
wait for Geshe La to build a
college in Moscow or
Singapore or
Ho Chi Minh, you know. If you have $5,
then start.
And uh it's courage. It's courage makes
the place, okay? Not the money.
The money comes later.
Okay?
Uh
this is an important thing. And I I
think I'll stop here today. And then
I'll take some questions, Tim.
I'll take We only have time for a few,
but I like this
This is a kind of a sad
scene.
This picture
in the painting is today.
in the painting
is today.
This is the day that Tsongkhapa died,
okay? This is the day that Tsongkhapa
left this world.
Okay? We don't say die. We don't say
Lama died. We say this is the day that
the Lama left this world, okay? And this
is the painting
in the painting
you can see
this is the day that Tsongkhapa left
this world. It's this holiday today.
Why we make the candle today?
One reason is he left the world on this
day. And we are asking him to come back,
okay?
And
it's very interesting Tsongkhapa
if you can see in his right hand
he has Lama hat. He has yellow Lama hat.
Okay?
And he's giving the hat to Gyaltsab Je,
to his student, okay? His best student,
number one student. He is giving the hat
to his student. And actually that hat uh
I'm going to get you. Hold on. Hang on.
So, this is Geshe Geshe hat.
Okay? And
uh this hat I got when I became Geshe.
And
in the monastery when the kids get this
hat
they use it like Frisbee.
They like to throw the hat to each other
like this.
And it spins very nice
when you throw it to your friend. You
can spin the hat and you can throw it to
your friend, you know.
So, actually how Tsongkhapa
gave the hat to his student.
Here he said very respectfully
giving the hat to his main student and
then he died.
Then he passed away.
But really in the story
he threw the hat
like a frisbee
to his student Gyaltsab Je. And Gyaltsab
Je caught the hat, you know.
And then it's a sign that Tsongkhapa
wants
more future generations
to follow Tsongkhapa's teaching. He
wants future generations
each generation
should teach the next generation.
Argon, yay yay, abuelo
grandfather, Geshe Michael
should teach student
and pass on the hat. Okay, Jenny, can
you catch the hat?
Okay, I'm throwing you one hat.
So, you know, grandpa should
grandpa should teach good students
around the world
in different countries.
And then you have to become the teacher
and you have to teach your students,
okay? It's not
my job to teaching.
You have to learn
and then I throw the hat to you in every
country.
Russia, Vietnam
Japan
different countries, Taiwan. You have to
catch the hat.
And then you become the teacher for your
place and you become the teacher for
your generation. Then you have to find
$5
and start to build something.
And the money will come, don't worry
about it. I I think it's very
interesting.
This painting in the Mongolian temple,
the paint cracked here
in Tsongkhapa's head, you see?
That's not paint. This is uh cracking
of the old paint.
But it's To me, I always thought it was
very interesting.
This is the day that uh Tsongkhapa left
his body.
And you can see the paint cracked uh
right here in his head.
And to me it always seemed like he was
leaving his body, you know, in in that
in that painting, okay?
Okay, so Tim,
uh let's go to some questions.
Do you have any?
Let's just do a few.
Great Geshe, that's the first
Oh, one more thing.
Hey Tim, can I show something?
Yeah, yeah.
Uh I'll show you tomorrow. I'll show you
tomorrow. Okay, let's go ahead. Uh
All right. So so the first question,
Geshe, is um
what are the We were You were talking
about finding your heart teacher. What
are some of the seeds that we can use to
What can we do to plant the seeds for
our heart teacher? And then secondly,
what does it feel like when we finally
found them? How do we know that this is
the one?
Um
um
I have a lot of ideas about it, but I'll
share a few.
Uh
I have many friends uh in America,
hippies,
uh 50 years ago, 40 years ago.
They say, "I want to find my heart
teacher, you know.
I'm going to go to India.
Uh I'm going to go to Himalayas.
And uh I will find my teacher there, you
know." And uh
I like to say uh if you plant the the
seeds,
your teacher has to come to you. You
see, you don't have to go to Himalayas.
Uh
What's the Himalaya is two things.
Highest mountain in the world, very
cold.
And secondly, best place to get diarrhea
in the whole world. If you want to get
diarrhea,
you can go to India, you can go to
Himalayas.
Okay? So, you don't have to go to
other country, you don't have to
You're not going to find teacher this
way, okay? I went to Himalayas.
I suffer in the Himalayas
with diarrhea and cold and
Then, when I came home, I found my
teacher is a 45 minutes away from my
house.
You know,
uh
So,
uh you can bring the teacher to you,
okay? You have to be like a beautiful
flower,
and the bee will come to you. It's very
difficult
to catch a bee.
But, if you have a beautiful flower,
the bee will come to you, you know? So,
my suggestion,
uh help all those teachers like Gen Wang
all over the world, help them.
Be a volunteer, you know?
Help them get the place, help them clean
the books,
help them give the teaching, help them
do the tech.
Be a volunteer. I was a volunteer for 25
years.
You know, people say, "Oh, Geshe La, you
have so many volunteers. You have
thousand volunteers in the world." Hey,
I was the only volunteer for 25 years. I
washed dishes for 8 years.
Okay? I was the dishwasher for 8 years.
You know, and this is the how you make
the seeds, okay? So,
help the Dharma,
help the teachers,
serve the teachers,
you know, and by the way,
uh those human teachers are not perfect,
okay? They get upset sometimes.
They get jealous sometimes. They make
mistakes sometimes.
They are They are human. They are
person, you know, they're also
trying to practice the path, okay? If
you see teacher do Teacher gets upset,
or I don't know, teacher does something
wrong, then don't get disappointed,
okay? Uh
they are trying
to be a good person. They are not
perfect, okay? It's It's not We are not
perfect people, okay?
Uh my teacher
My teacher had 100 200 students.
Uh he fired all of them.
You know, he got in fight with all of
them.
Uh I was the only survivor
uh in the house. I'm the only one who
survived
from 100 people who live with him, you
know, cuz he's so angry person
and so tough
and so rough person, you know, and
everybody from Princeton they used to
tell me uh
"Oh, that Tibetan lama, he taking your
money, you know, he's
you are working so hard for him. You
working all day, volunteer for him.
And he's like angry person. Like why Why
you stay there? Why you work Why you
work for him, you know?"
And
I plant the seeds
for my teacher to be a perfect teacher.
You see? I don't uh
I don't wait for the teacher to be
perfect.
I make the teacher perfect, okay? So, by
planting your own seeds,
by being a good person,
by meditating,
by studying Dharma,
by not getting angry. Hey Jenny, my
teacher refused to be vegetarian.
He
He You know, when he meets the other
Lama,
he will introduce me to the other Lama.
He will say, "This is my student.
His name is Mike."
Uh he gave up
He He couldn't give up I'm sorry. He
will introduce me like this. Mike gave
up eating meat,
but he didn't give up his klesha. He
didn't give up his negative emotion.
He will introduce me like this to the
other teacher.
He will say, "This is Mike.
He gave up meat,
but he couldn't give up his anger, his
desire, his jealousy.
He will introduce me this way, you know.
And uh
So,
he will make fun of me that I don't eat
meat, you know.
And he eats meat, you know. Then I say,
"I'm going to change this, you know."
So, I change change change my seed.
Change my seed. Change my seed.
When he was 70 years old, he gave up
meat.
Suddenly,
he he gave up eating meat. He said, "You
know, I decide not to eat meat anymore."
You know. And so,
the teacher also come from your seeds,
okay? The teacher also come from your
seeds. So, how to meet your heart
teacher?
Plant the seeds
by volunteer
to help the teaching.
And then you you create the heart
teacher. You make the heart teacher.
They come to you. It's like the husband
in the kitchen.
Okay? The Lama don't come from the Lama.
The Lama come from you. The heart
teacher come from you. It's like the
husband in the kitchen. It's the same.
Okay? If you want to meet your heart
teacher,
then help the Dharma to spread.
Help help organize teachings, be a
volunteer, work hard. I I clean the
dishes. I was full-time dishwasher for 8
years.
Uh then I was part-time dishwasher for
17 years.
And I make my teacher perfect, you know.
I I plant the seeds
to have a perfect teacher, okay? So,
that's how you find your heart teacher.
How do you know
when you meet them?
There's a famous quotation in the book,
and it says, "You know you met your
heart teacher
is the person who helped you the most to
be a good person. Who helped you the
most
to become a good person
is your heart teacher. That's your heart
teacher, okay?
Which teacher helped you the most
to be a good person,
then that's your heart teacher, okay?
That's how you know your heart teacher,
okay?
Okay, Tim.
You want to stop there, or you want one
more question?
Let's go one more question.
Okay, boss.
Um
so uh
it's been said that when you start
serving a teacher, someone who has a a
high karma as like a high karmic object,
lots of
old bad seeds ripen.
Um could you talk a little bit about
this? So, why is that the case, and and
how long do we have to suffer with that?
Yeah, uh
it's absolutely true, you know, when you
meet your teacher,
two things happen.
You have chance to collect good karma,
and you are burning off your bad karma
very fast, very very fast, okay?
So, there will be many problems with
your teacher, okay?
Uh
and you should be happy
with those problems. Uh we have a
we have a uh special DCI new advanced
level DCI
this month
uh January
uh
we are going to talk about
how to turn a problem
into a masterpiece, you know? Like how
to make a problem
into something very, very, very
beautiful, okay? And that's the new DCI
level
for January, okay? We will start in
January 12 new DCI levels.
The first level
is how to take a problem
and how to turn it into something very,
very beautiful, okay? So,
it's normal
with your teacher
that you will have some serious
problems, okay? It's normal. If you
don't have any problems
with your teacher
there's a something wrong. That's a
problem, okay? So, when you meet your
teacher
it's like you got married, right? It's a
honeymoon
for a few months, you know? You feel
very happy
you feel very spiritual. The teacher
looks very perfect
uh
for a few months, you know? Then you
start to have problems.
You know, then you see the teacher got
angry
or the teacher want money or or
something will happen, you know?
And teacher will yell at you
teacher will get angry at you
and you just have to be happy, okay? You
just have to say
"I don't care." You know, teacher angry
at me, I don't care.
You know, teacher yell at me, I don't
care, you know? I want to help the whole
world.
I want to be the light in the world. So,
don't get upset.
Don't get discouraged.
Don't quit.
Okay, if you quit this teacher, it's
like divorce, you know?
Then, you're going to divorce the next
one and the next one and the next one
and the next one. I think 90% of
people who get one divorce get a second
divorce, you know?
So,
my my experience
uh
it's very difficult
to serve a teacher. It's very, very
difficult.
And you will have many bad days and many
doubts. Uh
and you just have to have fun
and laugh and say, "Ah!
Okay, he's yelling at me today. She's
yelling at me today. Okay.
That's all right, you know? Uh
I can do it. I can do it, you know? So,
don't don't be too serious. Okay? I
think having fun
is very, very important with your
teacher. Okay? Have fun
with your teacher. Your teacher yell at
you 10 times,
then laugh 10 times and and have fun. Go
play some rock and roll or something,
you know? And uh don't get so serious.
Okay?
And uh have fun
with your teacher. It'll be okay. Later,
it will be okay. You are burning
your bad seeds. You are burning up your
bad seeds. Okay? Teacher will get angry.
Teacher will yell at you. Teacher will
be upset. Teacher will do something
wrong.
Oh, it's all coming from me. It's all
coming from me.
It's like the husband in the kitchen.
Your teacher
is the same as the husband in the
kitchen. They're coming from you, okay?
So, okay. Tomorrow is a new day.
Tomorrow, I will be a a better student.
Tomorrow, my teacher will
give me a hug.
Uh Uh tomorrow, my teacher will praise
me, you know. So, don't get so serious.
I think what why I survived
in the Mongolian temple
this one hippie survived
uh
cuz I have fun. I just have fun, you
know. I don't take so serious, you know.
Uh
usually when you get upset at your
teacher, it's your own pride. It's your
own pride. It's not the teacher. It's
your own pride, okay? So,
when there's trouble with your teacher,
just have fun, you know. Do something
good. I I like to go ride my bicycle
or I will play some rock and roll or
like that. I'm not allowed to play rock
and roll in the Mongolian
uh temple.
But, I have secret earphones
in my monk's room, you know. And when my
teacher yell at me, I can go listen to
rock and roll a little bit
and have fun, okay? So, don't get so
serious.
You know, don't don't be so serious. The
The student is usually too serious,
okay?
Uh try to respect your teacher.
Try to listen to your teacher.
You will fail.
You will make mistake.
Teacher will get angry.
Then, just relax, okay? Don't don't
worry so much.
Just relax.
Have some fun.
And come back the next day.
And they will yell at you the next day.
And then, come back the next day. And
they will yell at you the next day.
And just keep coming back.
And your life will be very very happy.
You need a teacher. You cannot practice
this path without a teacher. It's not
possible. It's impossible, okay? You
need a teacher.
If your teacher's not perfect,
then make them perfect
with your seed. If your husband's not
perfect,
that come from you.
If your teacher's not perfect, that come
from you, okay? And you can fix it.
And you can have a perfect teacher.
All right, you guys. Tim, how about we
continue tomorrow?
I